Chapter 126.
The Life Boy.
Steering now southeastward by Ahab's leveled steel, and her progress solely
determined by Ahab's level log and line, the Peekquad held on her path towards
the equator, making so long a passage through such unfrequented waters,
describing no ships, and heirlong sideways impelled by unvarying trade
winds over waves monotonously mild. All these seemed the strange calm things
preluding some riotous and desperate scene. At last, when the ship drew near
to the outskirts, as it were, of the equatorial fishing ground, and in the
deep darkness that goes before the dawn, was sailing by a cluster of rocky
eyelets. The watch, then headed by flask, was startled by a cry so
plaintiffly wild and unearly, like half articulated wailings of the ghosts of
all Herod's murdered innocents, that one and all they started from their
reveries, and for the space of some moments stood, or sat or leaned, all
transfixidly listening like the carved Roman slave, while that wild cry
remained within hearing. The Christian or civilized part of the crew said it
was mermaids and shuddered, but the pagan harpineers remained unappalled.
Yet the gay mansmen, the oldest mariner of all, declared that the wild,
thrilling sounds that were heard were the voices of newly drowned men in the sea.
Below, in his hammock, Ahab did not hear of this till gray dawn, when he came to
the deck. It was then recounted to him by flask, not unaccompanied with hinted
dark meanings. He hollowily laughed, and thus explained the wonder. Those rocky
islands the ship had passed were the resort of great numbers of seals, and
some young seals that had lost their dams, or some dams that had lost their
cubs, must have risen nigh the ship, and kept company with her, crying and
sobbing with their human sort of whale.
But this only the more affected some of them, because most mariners cherish a
very superstitious feeling about seals, arising not only from their peculiar
tones when in distress, but also from the human look of their round heads and
semi-intelligent faces, seen peeringly uprising from the water alongside. In
the sea, under certain circumstances, seals have more than once been mistaken for men.
But the boings of the crew were destined to receive a most plausible confirmation
in the fate of one of their number that morning. At sunrise this man went from
his hammock to the mast head at the four. And whether it was that he had not
yet halfw sailors sometimes go aloft in a transition state, whether it was thus
with the man, there is now no telling.
But be that as it may, he had not been
long at his perch when a cry was heard, a cry and a rushing, and looking up they
saw a falling phantom in the air, and looking down, a little tossed heap of
white bubbles in the blue of the sea.
The life boy, a long, slender cask, was dropped from the stern, where it always
hung obedient to a cunning spring, but no hand rose to seize it. And the sun
having long beat upon this cask, it had shrunken so that it slowly filled, and
that parched wood also filled at its every pour, and the studded ironbound
cask followed the sailor to the bottom, as if to yield him his pillow, though in
sooththe but a hard one.
And thus the first man of the Peekqua that mounted the mast to look out for
the white whale on the white whale's own peculiar ground, that man was swallowed
up in the deep, but few perhaps thought of that at the time. Indeed, in some
sort they were not grieved at this event, at least as important, for they
regarded it not as a foreshadowing of evil in the future, but as the
fulfillment of an evil already preaged.
They declared that now they knew the reason of those wild shrieks they had
heard the night before, but again the old mansmen said nay.
The lost life boy was now to be replaced. Starbucks was directed to see
to it, but as no cask of sufficient lightness could be found, and as in the
feverish eagerness of what seemed the approaching crisis of the voyage, all
hands were impatient of any toil but what was directly connected with its
final end, whatever that might prove to be. Therefore, they were going to leave
the ship's stern unprovided with a boy, when by certain strange signs and
innuendos, Quiquake hinted a hint concerning his coffin. "A life boy of a
coffin," cried Starbucks, starting.
"Rather queer, that I should say," said Stub. "It'll make a good enough one,"
said Flask. "The carpenter here can arrange it easily."
"Bring it up. There's nothing else for it, said Starbucks, after a melancholy
pause. Rig it, Carpenter. Do not look at me, so the coffin, I mean. Dust thou
hear me? Rig it.
And shall I uh nail down the lid, sir?
Moving his hand as with a hammer? I And shall I uh the seam, sir? Moving
his hand as with a cocking iron. I and shall I then pay over the same with
pitch sir moving his hand as with a pitch pot away? What possesses thee to
this? Make a life boy of the coffin and no more. Mr. Stub, Mr. Flask, come
forward with me.
Off he goes in a huff. The hole he can
endure at the parts he bs. Now I don't like this. I make a leg for Captain
Ahab, and he wears it like a gentleman, but I make a band box for Quiqu, and he
won't put his head into it. Or all my pains to go for nothing with that
coffin. And now I'm ordered to make a life boy of it. It's like turning an old
coat, going to bring the flesh on the other side. Now I don't like this
cobbling sort of business. I don't like it at all. It's undignified. It's not my
place. Let tinkers brats do tinkerings.
We are their betters. I like to take in hand none but clean, virgin, fair, and
square mathematical jobs. Something that regularly begins at the beginning and is
at the middle when midway and comes to an end at the uh conclusion. Not a
cobbler's job that's at an end in the middle and at the beginning at the end.
It's the old woman's tricks to be giving cobbling jobs. Lord, what an affection
all women have for tinkers. I know an old woman of 65 who ran away with a
bald-headed young tinker once, and that's the reason I never would work for
lonely widow old women ashore when I kept my job shop in the vineyards. They
might have taken it into their lonely old heads to run off with me. But hi ho,
there are no caps at sea but snow caps.
Let me see. Nail down the lid. the seams. Pay over the same with pitch.
Batten them down tight. And hang it with the snap spring over the ship's stern.
Were ever such things done before with a coffin.
Some superstitious old carpenters now would be tied up in the rigging. Air
they would do the job. But I'm made of naughty ara hemlock. I don't budge.
crumpered with a coffin, sailing about with a graveyard tray. But never mind.
We workers in woods make bridal bedsteads and card tables, as well as
coffins and hurses. We work by the month or by the job or by the profit. Not for
us to ask the why and wherefore of our work, unless it be too confounded
cobbling. Then we stash it if we can.
Hm. I'll do the job now tenderly. I'll have me, let's see, how many in the
ship's company, all told, but I've forgotten. Anyway, I'll have me 30
separate Turks headed lifelines, each 3 ft long, hanging all around the coffin.
Then, if the hull go down, there'll be 30 lively fellows all fighting for one
coffin. A sight not seen very often beneath the sun.
Come hammer, cocking iron, pitch pot, and marling spike. Let's to it.